never giving you my Bitcoin. If you
don't know where the yield comes from,
you are the yield. If we continue to see
this productivity boom that we're seeing
primarily driven by AI right now, I
think money will change significantly
because I think we can get to a spot not
far from now where agents and otherwise
are actually going out there and working
on our behalf and a lot of these
microtransactions that we are never
really kind of privy to, right? It's
kind of going on in this, you know,
asynchronous world and I think that's
just a totally new concept that we're
not ready for. Plus, what Brian Johnson
says, don't die now. We have so much
time. What is that generation? I think
it will. Private Bitcoin transactions
are kind of the holy grail. Let's say
I'm making transactions and I don't want
my wife to know.
Hi, good to see you. Good to meet you
again.
Bitcoin is all
[Music]
Bitcoin yield is an often overlooked,
underdeveloped area in the crypto space.
A very important hot topic here at the
Las Vegas Bitcoin Conference, the
biggest Bitcoin conference in the world.
Rich Ryan joins us today. He is the
initial contributor to Core Dow. will be
talking about his project and his vision
for Bitcoin yield. Welcome to the show,
Rich. I am joined by Bonnie Chang. You
mentioned in one of your speeches that
the genesis of cordow came from when you
were back working. You had a I'll give
you I'll let you explain your back
story, but um you had looked at the
industry and you realized that nobody
was scaling Bitcoin to the same extent
that you're doing now per your words.
explain what you mean by not scaling
Bitcoin. So, I think it's helpful to to
go back to one, great to chat with you
both, but also to go back to kind of how
I got exposed to Bitcoin. So, I first
heard about Bitcoin back in 2011. Didn't
really get it. By 2013, I reread the
white paper and then it all clicked. It
was an alternative traditional financial
system, a non-s sovereign store of
value. And I got really excited about
that concept. And by the 2017 cycle, I
was all in. Like, this is what I want to
do the rest of my career. Got super
super excited about it. And I actually
found my way to Coinbase where I led
money engineering for four years. But
during that transition, I think we lost
a lot of what made crypto crypto. And
what I mean by that is we started to
trade off decentralization for
performance everywhere. And we saw this
really peak probably in the 2020 2021
cycle where you saw these tokens that
were 70% insiders, right? They weren't
decentralized at all. And we had really
started to bring more and more of just
like high throughput computing on chain.
But what got me excited was all these
decentralized concepts, right? No one
can control Bitcoin. It's non-s
sovereign. And we said, okay, how do we
go like kind of bring crypto back to its
roots? And we kind of went from first
principles and we said, okay, we need to
go scale Bitcoin. Bitcoin is a multi-
trillion dollar asset, but it has very
little utility today besides just being
a store of value. Store of value is
amazing and as I refer to it, a really
sick gold. And we, you know, have done a
great job of building this collateral.
But what we needed was native yield. We
needed the ability to go put your
Bitcoin to work in a high throughput
environment like core. And that's what
we set out and we actually launched in
early 2023 before Bitcoin got cool
again, right? Bitcoin got cool with
ordinals and then BRC20s and all that
sort of stuff and probably peaked in
terms of interest from like a retail
side in 2024. But now you're seeing this
2025 cohort really that's come out of
the ETFs where it's now a financial
assets institutional asset and there's
just so much work that can be done and
we've probably penetrated 1% of
Bitcoin's potential. Why? Let's just
philosophically speaking, why would you
even need yield on Bitcoin? And a purist
would say
just look at proof ofstake systems
instead if you want yield that already
exists. Why are you trying to fit a cube
into a round hole? Uhhuh. So I would I
don't think it's a a square peg and a
round hole if you will. It's being a
store of value is amazing and that's
very useful but if you can have yield
you unlock a new wave of products. So a
good example from like a cryptonative
lens is Ethereum. So Ethereum postmerge
when you got yield really defi explosion
really kicked off again because now you
could have more protocols that are kind
of similar to financial primitives. Good
example of that would be like Pendle,
right? Where you have the ability to
split your principal token, your yield
token, which is kind of similar to like
coupon stripping and things like that
that you would have in traditional
financial system. And this is what
Bitcoin's been missing because it's
historically been negative carry. This
has always been a cost to just holding
Bitcoin rather than putting your bit or
your cash in like money market funds,
etc. So now you can have Bitcoin in your
own self-custody, stake it with core,
earn passive yield on your Bitcoin, and
if you want to go wrap that or bridge it
or have an LST where you go bring it
into a money market fund or you want to
trade per, you can do all that. But the
idea is you have this large capital base
that's very being used very
inefficiently today. Why would you not
want to go create more use cases for
that bitcoin? So just for my audience
who may not be familiar with you, what
is core dowo? How does it work? Just
dovetailing off of what you just said.
So core is a bitcoinpowered blockchain.
So on one side we've got the largest
bitcoin defi ecosystem. There's about
half a billion in TVL, 150 projects that
are live and about a million weekly
active users. So it's a pretty healthy
and developing ecosystem. And the other
side is the highest yielding Bitcoin
staking protocol. And the idea is
instead of just having the normal L1
utility of being a gas token staking
governance, you now have a fourth
utility which is to go earn passive
yield on your Bitcoin. And both sides
feed the other, right? As you get more
and more more activity on the L1, you
get higher yields. As you get more
demand for the the staking yield, you
see more and more activity in the
ecosystem. And they work in this
reflexive loop because they're all
centered around the core token and that
ecosystem. Core has very special
relationship with Bitcoin where our
consensus mechanism rewards 75% of the
Bitcoin hash that's currently securing
the core chain as well as about 7,500
Bitcoin that's helping to secure the
ecosystem. So, we want to do is build a
Bitcoin align chain because ultimately
we want to be the second asset that
Bitcoiners care about because they can
go take their Bitcoin and leave it on L1
if they want to just have it in cold
storage, but if they want to go earn
passive yield, they want to go put it to
work, then they can bring it over to
core to go do so. I think the most
important question people ask is what is
my risk?
So, the the how I always like to kind of
reframe that one as well is if you don't
know where the yield comes from, you are
the yield, right? And we know BlockFi
Genesis, Celsius, and probably several
other people that are at this conference
today that we haven't named yet. When
you see centralized lending and that
sort of stuff come back, it's usually
like a topy signal. And it's like you
have to be really care careful and
really judicious. And Bitcoin is the
most precious asset in the world. There
will only ever be 21 million Bitcoin.
It's the only asset that people can
never have enough of. So if you're going
to put your Bitcoin to work in some
system, you have to understand the
underlying mechanism with how that yield
is generated, how it's sustainable, etc.
So in core system, you time lock that
Bitcoin on the Bitcoin L1. So what that
means is you use a Bitcoin native op
code. You only have to trust Bitcoin,
but you're encumbering those funds for a
period of at least one day. So when
you're doing that, you cannot sell that
Bitcoin for up to a minimum of one day.
So you'd have liquidity risk. That's the
only thing. If you were going to go take
that Bitcoin and sell it, you cannot do
that until that time lock expires. But
when it comes to trade-offs, that's the
most minimal trade-off that you can make
because you can do this for while
retaining full self custody. you've no
counterparty risk and most people don't
want to sell their Bitcoin anyways. So,
are you even really making a trade-off
is is a great question. But by doing
that time lock, you're helping to secure
COR's chain and we you receive block
rewards and transaction fees for doing
so. And if you just stake your Bitcoin,
you earn one rate, but if you stake both
Bitcoin and Core, you earn much higher
rates. And that's how we blend these two
communities over time. Because I think
there's a little bit of a um assumption
that's incorrect where people think
Bitcoiners will accept any rate, but
that's not true. What Bitcoiners want to
do is they have to have some amount of
inertia that gets them to go get
involved in these systems. And that is
very patient capital, but you have to
have attractive rates and you have to
have a a system that Bitcoiners
ultimately are comfortable with. And
this is the first thing that I've been
comfortable putting my Bitcoin in. We
designed it for Bitcoiners by
Bitcoiners.
Um, a lot of Bitcoin treasury companies
talk about Bitcoin yield as well, but
those terms are, I think, very different
from your Bitcoin yield. When they say
Bitcoin yield, it means Bitcoin per
share sort of to say. Can you explain to
the viewers what is your Bitcoin yield?
It would be in other tokens. So
fundamentally what Bitcoiners are doing,
whether it's in a treasury company or
individually, they're usually trying to
acquire more Bitcoin, right? Like that's
the name of the game. So how these
treasury companies mostly work is
through financial engineering, right?
And that's been very accive for these
people to essentially use this NAV
premium to go get more Bitcoin to the
treasury companies. that NAV premium as
we're seeing is now compressing, right?
And as this trade becomes more and more
crowded and there's now several of these
launching every day, they're going to
need other sources of yield that are not
just financial engineering. So, we
actually work symbiotically with these
other uh with these other treasury
companies. We have a number of
discussions ongoing where they can use
that Bitcoin that they have today that's
in their custody to go earn passive
yield, which increases their Bitcoin per
share if they're just trying to go
acquire more Bitcoin. Or what they can
do is hold that in core and then go
stake more Bitcoin. And that's also what
we're seeing as a pattern of people who
have been staking in in the core
ecosystem for uh for some period of
time. But ultimately, you can think
about core's infrastructure is really
like the backend yield infrastructure
for Bitcoin. And that's how we want to
power not just like new, you know,
financial products on Wall Street, but
also folks that are going to acquire
large amounts of Bitcoin like these
treasury companies.
What I like about your work isn't just
about core, but you also kind of are a
visionary in a way about how Bitcoin
should be used. Going back to what you
said earlier about Bitcoin's utility
being more than just a store of value.
One of the things you said which I like
is how Bitcoin could be used in the new
financial system. For example, borrowing
against her Bitcoin without the use of
financial intermediaries which is a new
concept for a lot of people. How would
life look like in that system? So I
think we've really just scratched the
surface of Bitcoin being used like and
historically we've seen Bitcoiners just
being held by like large individuals
maybe family offices. Then with the
ETFs, we saw more broad-based retail
adoption for the first time. Buying
pizza, don't forget. Yeah, buying pizza.
Although he still has a ton of Bitcoin.
That's that's one of my favorite
stories. Uh it's always like, you know,
people always laugh at at LLO, but he's
got a ton of Bitcoin. I think he's doing
just fine. Um but but but now what we're
seeing is like these more kind of
traditional rappers that are opening up
more and more groups to Bitcoin holding
that couldn't self custody or refuse to
self custody for a long time. If you can
do that, you still should, but the vast
majority of people will probably never
do that. and they'll use one of these
rappers, but these rappers allow you to
express different views on Bitcoin. And
I think that's what's really critical.
So, if we think about the the ETFs,
right, the view was I want Bitcoin
upside exposure, but I want to deal with
none of the risks of like holding my own
Bitcoin. So, that's one view that people
had. That is now going to naturally go
into like what we already have, which is
Kor's, you know, uh, staking ETPs that
we have live in Europe. We're going to
have staking ETFs not far from now. So,
it's going to be people who want
Bitcoin. They want passive yield their
Bitcoin in a rapper. So you're
increasing your Bitcoin per share, if
you will, by having that. And then
you're also going to have other sorts of
like structured products and derivatives
that I think will take quite a bit of
mind share and flows over the next
coming years. So one that I've been
chatting with, you know, a number of
issuers about that I think we'll see
within the next, let's call it 6 to 12
months will be uh will be these like
structured products that essentially
have the tails clipped and what you'll
have is like maybe 20% max draw down on
your Bitcoin and you'll have like
probably 60% max upside. And for a lot
of people, having a V dampened Bitcoin
is actually a lot more appealing because
they don't want to be around for the
full Bitcoin roller coaster. And we'll
continue to see more and more of these
rappers in these traditional lenses. And
I think the flows will continue to grow.
And those additional sources of all will
also open up a larger Bitcoin
derivatives market. And the Bitcoin
derivatives market at scale should
roughly be 5 to 10 times the Bitcoin
spot market. So we haven't even
scratched the surface of what this is
going to look like from uh from kind of
a traditional rapper perspective. Let's
give a practical example. Practical
example to the layman watching this
right now. Suppose I have a bunch of
Bitcoin in my in my wallet. I don't know
what to do with it. I like to buy a
house. I don't want to spend my Bitcoin.
I like to use as collateral to get a
mortgage. Can I do that? How? Totally.
So, if you have Bitcoin and you're doing
it like let's say on Bitcoin main chain,
right? What you can do is you can find a
lender that's willing to borrow against
that Bitcoin. And there's a number of
product services been around for a long
time. Yeah. But there's always been a
trade-off there, which has been, okay,
if I want to go do that, how do I go
give you my Bitcoin or take it out of my
self- custody? That's always been a
challenge. So, we're seeing some people
do is they're actually starting to lend
against staked Bitcoin. This is
something that Maple Finance will do and
they have a great partnership with Core
where they'll actually lend against
staked Bitcoin and now you can go get,
you know, some of that leverage that you
might want to go buy a house. But I
think what we're also seeing is people
that are taking their Bitcoin, they're
going to wrap it and bring it onto a
protocol like Collend, which is the
borrow end of the core ecosystem, and
they'll borrow USDT, USDC, etc. that
they can then go and bring that to, you
know, whatever their broker is to to go
buy a house. But we're still in the
early phases of this. And I think we'll
continue to see this pattern grow very
quickly because essentially what we've
created is a way to have self-repaying
Bitcoin loans. And I think this is going
to be a buy now pay never type, you
know, moniker that we'll see over the
next few years really start to grow
because you're not going to want to take
counterparty risk. You're going to want
to go get leverage and you're going to
want to go continue to to grow your
Bitcoin portfolio or your traditional
asset space. Why do you say sell never?
What does that mean? Great question. Um,
so when I say buy now, sell never, it's
the idea is that the Bitcoin itself is
growing. So the LTV of that loan with
staking rate plus just the dollar value
of that going up is decreasing every
day. And if you think about it's like
imagine if you took out a loan, you
know, Bitcoin was 10 grand, now it's
100. You went from maybe like, you know,
10% LTV to 1% LTV, right? And and you'll
see more and more of that, I think,
become commonplace because we're going
to get to a world where Bitcoin is the
most precious asset, I think, for
everyone in the world. And it's going to
essentially act as a savings account,
right? So, what you're going to do with
fiat debasement, all these other like,
you know, kind of macro shifts that, you
know, we all know and love, uh, because
it's good for our bags, but bad for
other things, right? um you're going to
just see people stockpile more and more
Bitcoin, but you still have day-to-day
expenses that are in forms of dollars,
right? So, you're going to stockpile
Bitcoin, borrow against it, pay off,
you'll get your earnings from your
normal job, whatever, pay off that, but
it's going to be kind of that
alternative traditional financial system
that we always wanted, right? Like, if
you can have Bitcoin being your savings
account, your need for banks is that
much less. And if you can have uh the
ability to collateralize that in a
self-custodial way, you get to really
powerful places where you get rid of
these intermediaries that we've been
trying to do for so long. If a bank
comes in and say, "I like what core is
doing. I'm going to start my own
blockchain doing exactly what you do."
Is that a crazy strong competitor? I
don't think they'd copy us and be the
yield layer. We actually work very
symbiotically with folks like banks and
we have a number of, you know,
conversations ongoing. I firmly believe
that in the US most major banks will
have Bitcoin custody, not crypto
custody. people will say Bitcoin custody
either through a Coinbase or potentially
direct within the next 5 years and I
think you'll start to see okay we've got
Bitcoin on balance sheet how do the next
thing is how do I go earn on that
Bitcoin right that's the natural next uh
next evolution that's exactly where we
want to come in right we want to be this
backend yield infrastructure for Bitcoin
so as long as you have Bitcoin on your
balance sheet or customer Bitcoin
somewhere you can now go put that to
work in our system with no principal
risk and that's ultimately where we will
help kind of bring these products and
services to market because everyone will
want Bitcoin. Everyone will want Bitcoin
yield. Let's just address the risk that
Bonnie brought up earlier and get into
more detail. Do you actually custody the
Bitcoin yourself? We do not. It never
leaves your custody. Okay. So, like this
is another one that I kind of common
line that I say, never send me your
Bitcoin. Okay? Like I I I never want it.
I would never send my Bitcoin to someone
else. So, I would never ask someone to
do the same. Okay. So, there's no risk
of you just taking the Bitcoin is
somebody
might ask. Correct. Because you're just
time locking it on the Bitcoin at L1. So
from like a technical perspective, that
UTXO never leaves your wallet. You just
cannot spend it. So the risk that you
have is liquidity risk because if you
cannot spend it, you cannot move it to
sell it or bring it to an exchange or
anything of that nature. Is there a
staking period? Minimum of one day.
Okay. Is there a maximum? There is no
maximum. I'm guessing the yield goes up
with more time. Not currently. That is
something that we've discussed at
length. the having additional like yield
curve components on top of these staking
dynamic is a lot for the market to
absorb right now. Okay, because we
already have a nonlinear staking curve.
So what you now wind up with adding
duration on top of that is you get a
multivariate nonlinear curve and we've
been trying to figure out how to explain
this to people. Um but but it will go
live not far from now. If I were PIMCO
or any bond fund, okay, and I go to you
and say, "Hey, could you help me
construct a Bitcoin fixed income product
using Core Dow, how would you respond to
that?" The answer is yes. Like you can
kind of almost think about what we're
doing is really like a Bitcoin bond
layer. That's right. Like like that.
That's kind of the idea. So what we want
to enable is people to build additional
products and services on top of what
we're doing, right? And this is a good
example of like what Maple has launched
with the with the LST. The idea is okay
if you have Bitcoin how do I go get
enough core to then go get these high
yields and they tokenize that entire
trade and then soon there'll be a liquid
staking derivative that will come off of
it. But we're going to see more and more
of these that will take on additional
sources of risk if you will. So another
example that I give people all the time
is pretty common trade is like Bitcoin
basis trading or they'll do like call
overriding right so if you can bring our
staking yield as your collateral into
one of these other trades now you can go
earn let's call it you know 2 to 4%
whatever that is plus you get the
staking rate okay that trade now gets
significantly more profitable. So this
is how like we're that underlying layer
that people hedge funds etc can build on
top of. One more follow-up question. So
there's no such thing as a free lunch.
What does a staker give up? In other
words, what does it cost for the staker
to earn the yield? So in this case, what
they're doing is, and again, it wouldn't
be just in Kor's ecosystem. You can
think about this in any staking
ecosystem. When you are giving your
voting power to some validator, you are
now delegating the responsibility to one
vote on governance and these other
pieces, but you cannot move those funds
for some period, right? Like you have a
liquidity duration, but that is not
unique to our ecosystem, right? In the
example of Ethereum, what you're doing
is you're taking 32 ETH, you bring it to
a validator and then that 32 ETH until
you get it back from that, you cannot
actually use that for anything else.
Very similar in core system. I'm trying
to imagine my mom watching this and her
question would be, okay, well, you say
Bitcoin is digital gold. Now, if I put a
va a go my gold in a vault,
why why do I get yelled?
So, I think the idea of like putting
your Bitcoin in a vault is what we want
to kind of kill off to a degree. Okay?
Because I think that's how we've maybe
not kill off, maybe that's too strong,
but the idea of not using your Bitcoin
we think is just not utilizing it to the
fullest capacity that it can have. And
like as someone who's been sitting on
Bitcoin now for, you know, over a
decade, that hasn't really left my
wallet for a long time, right? Like it's
just been this passive asset. But why
would you not want to go use your
Bitcoin in some way, shape or form? And
again, the leverage example that David
brought up, I think is a, you know,
pretty common one. People don't want to
pay taxes in their Bitcoin ever else.
They just want to borrow dollars to go
kind of hit these expenses. Okay, that
makes sense. Even that, in my opinion,
is like a significant step up to just
get people comfortable with doing that.
But all of this is a continuum. So like
many people, the only thing they want to
do with Bitcoin is just sit on it today.
We can only offer them education. For
people that, you know, might want
passive yield, awesome. You can go into
staking or dual staking. Okay, if you're
ready for full Bitcoin, DeFi and that
sort of thing, you can wrap, swap,
bridge, whatever. That's a much much
smaller segment than where everyone else
is. What we want to do is just kind of
get people products and services that
meet their goals. But I think the idea
of it being like locked away and you
throwing away the key, that's an idea
that we want to broaden the, you know,
the Overton window and people's, you
know, thought process because you don't
need to do that unless you just want to
do that. I guess my actual question
would be how does that help your
ecosystem? me putting my digital gold um
in your or in a vault. How does that
help core? Like why are you paying me a
yield to do that? Yeah, because you're
helping to secure our network. So that
is I think what a lot of people do not
understand. So and I think people
haven't really gotten used to having a
consensus mechanism that has multiple
ingredients. And we're not the only one,
but I think we're probably the only one
that has three. So we have 75% of the
Bitcoin hash. There's about 230 million
core and about 7500 Bitcoin. That all
factors into core security. And the way
to think about it is in most ecosystems
you just have one hard to acquire thing,
right? So you just have Ethereum or
Salana or one of these things. And to go
attack it, we have to do is get a large
quantum of that attack validator set and
go from there. In core ecosystem, you
need to get three hard to acquire
things. It's core, it's Bitcoin, and
it's also this Bitcoin hash. And that's
very valuable to us, not just from our
alignment with Bitcoin, but also the
security and resiliency of the network.
And that's why we we pay the rewards for
the security that folks are uh
exchanging by, you know, locking up
their their Bitcoin hash or um or the
core.
What are the tax implications of Bitcoin
yield? I'm just curious since you
brought up tax. So in terms of tax, it's
income in most jurisdictions. I'm not a
tax professional. I don't play on TV. I
guess that's the classic varies where
you are, but just generally in
principle, what does account as?
Generally, it's income. Okay. Right. and
it's priced at the time of when you
receive it. Again, nothing unique about
our system in that way. But um staking
is inefficient from that point of view.
Okay. Well, let's talk about um uh
something new that's uh that you're
doing. So um you Well, actually before
we talk about this new system, let's
just talk about the growth so far. Core
Dow's grown from about 18 million users
to 52.6 million addresses just in the
past year. what contributed to that
growth? So, I think what we've seen over
the past year is one this like shift of
people being more open to go do stuff
with with their Bitcoin for the first
time. And again, that's a decade long
journey that will take to fully realize
it. But we've had a big growth in terms
of products and services and real
businesses being built on core as these
things scale up. And I think we're past
the phase of crypto where like it's just
you launch a token, there's no product
market fit and you kind of go away. A
lot of the businesses on core are more
focused on revenue generation and
building for the long term. And that's
something that a we look for in builders
that we want to help promote and go to
market with, but also we need these
folks to be able to have like long-term
sustainable businesses. So a good
example is one like coland, right? So
borrow and lend is isn't sexy, I would
say, but it's key piece of all financial
systems is debt, right? And being able
to borrow and have liquid markets. And
that business has has grown from early
last year of not existing to now
hundreds of millions of DVDL. And it's
got a fairly active market and there's
quite a few participants because it
meets a need for Bitcoiners, right?
Whether they want to borrow dollars
against their Bitcoin or they want to
borrow different assets to go use the
core ecosystem for trading. But you have
a market there that's forming and you
have more and more people coales around
these products. And then on the other
side, we've had quite a bit of growth in
protocols like BitFlux. Bitflex is a
stable swap for Bitcoin. There's so many
Bitcoin derivatives, LSTs. As those grow
and proliferate, you get more and more
trading volume, more and more real
activity. And then I'd say the kind of
final thing is we're trying to onboard
more and more people into this ecosystem
that may have historically not had a lot
of great DeFi opportunities. So one of
the ones that I'm you know super excited
about is group called Nawa Finance. Nawa
Finance is the first Sharia compliant
DeFi aggregator. So the entire um you
know is Islamic world has been pretty
much you know barred from DeFi for the
last you know since DeFi was created. So
now there's actually products and
services that can address hundreds of
millions or billions of people around
the world. That's how you not only
expand the TAM but you have again real
products that deliver value for these
different you know communities and
there's a ton of um Bitcoin in that area
in particular that historically has been
locked out for yield opportunities and
now can go do that on core for the first
time. So I think it's a combination of
product market fit great builders great
protocols and then trying to do novel
interesting things. Why couldn't Islamic
world do staking again? So you need a
ruling on all of these things. Um, but
traditionally when you get to things
like lending, you get to haram yields.
So you get to things that are outlawed
in terms of earning uh in different
fashions. I'm not an Islamic finance
expert, don't get me wrong. Um, but we
have spent a significant amount of time
in that region to understand these
problems more to partner with amazing
builders and from an ecosystem point of
view, we want to have primitives that
they can build on top of to ultimately
uh provide value to their end users. How
what are they doing differently now?
It's not haram.
So it comes down to the sources of
yield, right? So staking can be a good
source of yield depending on how it's
generated. You can get into other sorts
of of protocols as well. You can think
of like interestbearing stables
potentially depending how the interest
is generated. But you have to go into
the underlying yield mechanisms of all
these protocols and essentially go all
the way through to a scholar to ensure
that this is actually okay because
otherwise if you wind up with um like
haram yields or just money that you
shouldn't have, you should not be able
to like profit off of that according to,
you know, kind of the classic teachers.
That's really interesting. Yeah. Let's
pitch this to some uh Islamic finance
people. Let's see what they think.
That's our producer over there. He's
he's Muslim. He's smiling the whole
time. Yeah. Well, we'll ask him. We'll
ask him for his feedback later, but
let's talk about uh LSTBTC.
It's uh it's a new liquid staking token
that you just launched. How does it
work? So, if we think about Kor's
Bitcoin staking, right? That was, you
know, broad-based acclaim, all that sort
of stuff. But in order to have a
healthier sustainable yield, we came up
with dual staking and the idea was to
have higher yields, you had to become a
participant in the core ecosystem. And
by acquiring a core and bitcoin
position, not only are you aligning the
two networks, but you now get much
higher yields. So as of now the just
base staking rates 10 to 30 bips the max
dual staking rates about 4 to 500 bips.
So you have a significant difference.
It's multiplicative and that's that
nonlinear staking curve that I
mentioned. So building off of that
there's this um kind of hurdle that a
lot of people have which is okay they
want to go get this high yield but they
only have Bitcoin. So, how do you go
make it a way for them to go get access
to that core to go put on that trade in
a really simple and combined way and
then be able to have the liquidity to go
bring that into DeFi or CFI ecosystems.
So, how the LST works, it's partnership
between us and Maple Finance. Bitcoin
comes in, core gets acquired uh using a
low LTV loan, core gets hedged, and then
the idea is you get this receipt token.
This receipt token you can bring into a
number of DeFi protocols when it goes
live in the next month or two or soon be
able to use as collateral on many of
these centralized exchanges. And that's
a big push for us because again, think
about like a non- retail use case,
market makers, etc. constantly are
posting Bitcoin collateral, right? So if
they posting Bitcoin collateral, why
would you not want yield bearing Bitcoin
collateral, right? It's a strictly
better option provided it's in a
custodian like a Bitco
that that list is expanding. But the
idea now is you get this, you know,
strictly better solution where you can
now go bring this and uh, you know, make
your strategies more profitable or at
least not negative carry. And the idea
between the um, behind the LST was no
longer having trade-offs between being
an institutional grade custody and
having best-in-class Bitcoin yield. You
can now have all the above. Okay. Now,
if I have my Bitcoin in Coinbase or
Binance, take me step by step. What
should I do to get all the benefits you
just mentioned? Oh man. Uh I don't want
to anger my my former folks over at
Coinbase. Um so we don't have
integrations with these exchanges today.
I think as time goes on, we will look to
make the product more and more
ubiquitous. Today, if you wanted to go
mint the LST, what you would have to do
is use one of the custodians that that's
in the network once it goes live. Or
what you'll be able to do soon enough is
to swap into it in DeFi protocols. So
what I'm asking is okay so a lot of
retail investors they have their Bitcoin
on a centralized exchange. So first they
have to transfer it out. So I I just
want to know what they would have to do
like each step what they would have to
do to have my Bitcoin earn yield. What
is this? So so sorry. So so two two
different two different questions if you
will. One is how do you take like your
native Bitcoin and get the LST? The
other is like how do you just go earn
yield on your Bitcoin? um they're using
the same underlying mechanism, but
they're actually two very very different
paths. So, in terms of the okay, how do
I go earn yield on my Bitcoin? Well, you
would withdraw it from your Binance,
your Coinbase, etc. You would then stake
it using a a wallet of your choosing or
to craft a transaction on your own. And
then you would optionally stake core
alongside of it. But that would be the
flow of I'm sitting on my Bitcoin. I
want to maintain it in in full self-
custody. I want to go earn passive
yield. And that's one approach. And
that's the majority of how people use it
today. With the LST, what you'd have to
do is go from native Bitcoin either
through a custodian to go mint the LST
or what you would do is you'd bring it
into a wrapped asset like a WBTC or
similar CBBTC and then you would trade
um to go get the LST in a D5 protocol.
And then if you had that LST, you now be
earning that passive yield alongside
just holding that token, right? But
these are, and this is where when I
refer to us as the like liquidity
infrastructure, it's that same dual
staking mechanic that's enabling all of
these different products and services
and also other amazing LSTs like solve
and that sort of thing that's also based
upon Coors yield. It's this primitive
that we've created for Bitcoiners to to
utilize. I think I'm hearing you putting
Bitcoin to work, right? Historically,
people want to put it in a safe, but
you're asking your Bitcoin, hey, go out
and work for me. to whatever degree
you're comfortable with. Like that's the
way to think about it where again some
people want to go to the total extreme
end and they want to like lever up and
do derivatives trading whatever else.
And for some people that's awesome, but
for a lot of people they want to just
kind of creek out of the door and they
want to just have passive yield and
that's also fine. And that's why we've
taken an approach of having different
products and services that match these
different end goals and also like the
trust risk assumptions etc. because
that's how we actually unlock the $2
trillion of Bitcoin. If I try to use,
you know, David's term of square peg and
a round hole, if I try to force you into
derivatives trading or something like
that, and that's not like I'm I'm going
to burn you and we're never going to be
able to have like a successful, you
know, symbiotic relationship.
What is the yield? I don't think we've
given a number yet. So, the yield
fluctuates. It's based on it's based on
market forces, right? Today, the low end
of that yield, if it's just Bitcoin, is
between 10 to 30 bips typically. And on
the high end, it fluctuates between 4 to
600 bips. market forces being like the
US 10 year interest rate or something
else. So today it's mostly the core
bitcoin ratio and then also how this
bitcoin gets staked because of that
nonlinear curve right so you have
different buckets and those different
buckets will impact that yield curve in
different ways I guess indirectly let's
say a fed funds rate cut or a hike would
that matter for the yield not directly
but indirectly it would affect people's
yield expectations that sort of thing
right so like in today's system if you
max dual stake your bitcoin you're
actually beating the the Fed funds rate
in Bitcoin terms. That's really
appealing, right? So, I think long term
there is some amount of like yield
targeting and kind of like, you know,
board of governors type thing that
eventually might, you know, get put in
place here as time goes on. But as of
now, I'd say that's more a how people
view these trades and how they want to
put it on if they want to go look at it
as like kind of competing with, you
know, the Fed funds rate or doing
something more exotic. And how would
that range be decided? Would it is there
is there a governance structure here or
is that it's just you and you know your
friends? No, there's a it core is a is a
DAO so there's like onchain voting that
goes into these things. Um but I would
say like to go into again that like kind
of thought process of how this impacts
things. The analogy is really to the
like traditional capital markets, right?
Where it's like, okay, you have this
risk-free rate. This risk-free rate goes
into, okay, what are the lending rates?
All these things kind of cascade off of
this. And this is exactly the vision of
how core will function. And we're
already starting to see this where
people say, okay, if I can go earn, you
know, let's say four to 6% of my
Bitcoin, why am I only getting, you
know, four and a half percent to go lend
out my Bitcoin, right? Like that is a
very different risk association for
maybe even less return. And what we're
ultimately trying to do is help people
one create a market for this and
actually give people more options but
two to push up the risk premia that
these other things are associated with
because if you can earn let's say you
know four to six% passively well when
they go get me to lend my Bitcoin maybe
I need 8 n 10%. Right? And I think
that's very healthy as we start to build
more and more Bitcoin capital markets
not just from like a retail perspective
but also a more institutional
perspective right? Um, in one of your
interviews you said LST
um, BTC can be used in basis trade and
I'm very interested how does that work?
So you can do onchain basis trades and
that sort of thing but those haven't
really scaled I think and and there's
been some folks that have tried that and
Salon and other ecosystems but the
ultimate goal is to have this LSTBTC be
this collateral asset on the largest
exchanges in the world. And the reason
that we want that is you can now bring
over that yield with you. And you can
think about USDE and some of these other
you know yield bearing um crypto
projects that have integrated with the
buy bits etc of the world and now you
have that yield it's a better collateral
for you than like a USDT
you know risk assumptions everything
involved there right but but with that
if you can now bring that over you can
now make your strategy that much more
profitable and if you look at Bitcoin
basis trading it's not the most
profitable strategy but it's very
reliable so now if you can go bring this
in as what we refer to as like a layer
deal or like a yield enhancer those
strategies get that much more profitable
and it's also a great driver of demand
for this product.
You brought up Okay, let's go back to
the risk question. You brought up the
Celsius BlockFi. I've actually had the I
don't know if you want to call it
pleasure or displeasure of interviewing
al Alex Mashinsky on many occasions in
the past and um I remember um we talked
about yield a lot and there was a debate
between Peter Schiff and Mashinsky that
I helped produce and in the conversation
about yield Schiff asked him how are you
generating double digit yields I mean
you must be taking a tremendous amount
of risk on the back end Alex's answer
was of course we're not later it was
shown that they were indeed taking on
excessive leverage which contributed to
their fall. If Schiff were sitting here
today and he's asking the same question,
9 10% of today's market condition seems
excessive, how can you convince us that
you're not another Celsius? So one, we
never take uh possession of the Bitcoin.
So it's always with you, right? But in
this case, we would never promise
something like 9 10% yield. It's all
driven by market forces. And I think
another example would be like a Terral
Luna, etc. where it was like, okay,
here's 20% no matter what the inputs
are, right? like that that system is
just unstable, right? So in our case,
like yeah, it's at 4 to 6% now. That
very well could be at a much lower
percentage over time. It depends on how
much comes into the protocol and how
much offsetting demand that there is,
but ultimately it has to float. But it's
not really the Bitcoin bond layer in in
COR's case that's where the excess risk
gets involved. It's what gets built on
top of it, right? Like we're this base
layer primitive that has, you know, no
principal risk associated with it. We
can't control what the hedge fund layer
does. Sure. Right. and and we'll see and
we've chatted with a number of these
protocols that want to go use our LST as
the input into lending strategies and
other things on top of it. And what they
need to do is disclose exactly how
that's going to go get used, right?
Because that's where you get to
compounding risk because not only are
you now transferring your Bitcoin into
one of these other protocols, but you
don't know exactly what they're doing,
but they should be compensating you for
whatever risk is going on there. Mhm. I
think if we look at BlockFi Genesis, um,
you know, Celsius, etc., not only was it
under collateralized lending, which
should already be like pretty far out on
the on the risk spectrum, but also maybe
some disclosures that weren't quite, you
know, what was actually going on and
like a lot of it was the GBTC and a few
of these other pieces that like unwound
in like relatively spectacular fashion.
But it's important that as soon as you
go into something that like is higher
risk or even low risk in our case, you
should understand exactly where the
yield comes from and then what you're
getting into. you probably talked to a
lot of institutions and hedge funds like
you mentioned. What are their concerns?
So the first thing that most people say
is like I'm never giving you my Bitcoin.
Like that that's the first thing that
everyone says and as you can tell it's
part of this conversation like that's
where a lot of these naturally go. And
that's the whole first thing is we need
to convince people that we don't
actually want your Bitcoin, right? Like
do not send it to us. We don't want
possession. If you send it to us, you
don't get more yield. Like you just give
us a new problem, right? Uh so so in
general like that's where a lot of these
go and the other piece is that we also
try to say that start with whatever
you're comfortable with. You might have
10,000 bitcoins start with one bitcoin,
right? Like you don't need to go all in
on day one. This is a multi-deade
project. You need to just scale in at
whatever you feel comfortable and get to
whether it's just pure Bitcoin staking
or dual staking. But that's a whole
process because historically what people
are trying to do with these institutions
is give me all of your Bitcoin. I'm
gonna go bring it into DeFi for you and
then with this DeFi, I'm going to give
you some amount of yield back. It's
going to be like pretty opaque and not
that transparent. And for some people
that's okay that are like on the
bleeding end of the risk spectrum, but
not the majority of institutions that we
talk to. We we're trying to build a
product that people can get comfortable
with and ultimately deploy in over time.
And that with our yield curve being 81
years on this very gradual emission, we
want people to, for lack of better
words, like set it and forget it with
kind of the products that they create
and build off of this yield. But we view
it as much more of like kind of an
enterprise, you know, selling process of
trying to go through all the different
details even down to questions like tax
and otherwise because these are the
questions the largest capital allocators
have and then it's, you know, 14 15 etc
touch points to get people to understand
exactly what they're going to deal with
before they ultimately deploy. But we
ultimately have to go at whatever pace
they want to move. So if I if I stake
both Bitcoin and core um every like the
Bitcoin yield so-called I'll just stake
it right and if I'm a big institution I
would ask
what what does it look like on my
balance sheet then?
Great question. This is where you get to
get into like
different financial regimes in like
different areas and that sort of thing.
But depending on how you acquire the
Bitcoin, acquire the core, they can
either be assets or liabilities, right?
Like in some cases, people will try to
borrow the core, they borrow the
Bitcoin, right? But you can kind of wind
up on either the right or the left side
depending on how that looks. But the
income of like the staking piece or
whatever would be revenue in this case.
I'd like to talk about you for a couple
minutes. Let's do it. So, in my
introduction, I alluded to the fact that
you've had a story career working in um
other exchanges leading up to your aha
moment. We need to stake yield uh stay
stake Bitcoin. We need to scale Bitcoin.
So, just walk us through your career and
I like to get a sense of how you think
the industry has shifted, but let's talk
about your career so far. Oh, man. We're
going down to like where do we start? Do
we start at the lemonade stand or do we
The first time you discovered maybe
crypto and ultimately leading up to
Coinbase and then now. Okay. So, back in
2011, I think it was it 2010 or 2011, we
got introduced to the Byzantine Generals
program, Byzantine General's problem as
part of this directed uh reading program
in college. And we had a professor that
was explaining this problem to us and we
didn't really understand it like and I
couldn't understand like why it was so
impressive and there's money in the
computer like you did you did
engineering uh so I studied uh
information systems economics okay which
is databases and econ like pre- crypto
like I didn't know it was exactly the
like intra spectrum that this would be
but they were just kind of where my
brain naturally went to and that's why
we were taking that class it was like
kind of peak stucks net like all of that
like computer hacking all that sort of
stuff was like very top of mind and as
part of that it didn't really resonate
because I was coming at it from probably
too academic of a perspective not really
understanding the global impact of what
something like this could have and then
in 2013 after I got like reintroduced to
Bitcoin went back to the white paper
again that's when it clicked for me as
wait a second we can actually
disintermediate banks maybe we can
actually build a better money and we
thought we were building money at that
point and I I don't think Bitcoin's
really money at this point what about
the white paper originally most appealed
to
I think the idea was having a non-s
sovereign store value like forever it's
like hey you have the US dollar it's
backed by you know the government and
guns and whatever else and it's like
well could you actually create something
that has value and by 2013 that was when
we had the second Bitcoin price runs
right up to like a thousand for the
first time and that was the first time I
was like wow people are actually valuing
this thing right like and I think we got
involved in the hundreds or whatever but
it was like wow this is really
interesting that other people view this
as valuable in a way that is totally
non-conensus, right? Like there's no
central bank of Bitcoin that is saying
this is what this is, we're author,
right? It was it was all a free market
dynamic. And that was what was so
appealing because that's when I got my
first like glimpse into the future, if
you will, of wow, I could see this being
the underpinning of like some new
disintermediated financial system. It's
funny that you brought up the white
paper is kind of your inspiration. I'll
get to the rest of your story because
what Satoshi wrote in that white paper
was that Bitcoin was meant to be a
decentralized peer-to-peer system, which
is not what you're building now. Like
there's, you know, we're not trying to
we're not trying to use core so I could
send Bonnie money, right? In a sense,
you can use core to to send Bonnie money
or send uh Bonnie Bitcoin. And it's
definitely like it's definitely like you
want my core. Okay, I won. Send your
core and your Bitcoin. Uh and and it's a
much more efficient um like cheaper way
to send Bitcoin and that sort of thing.
And that's important because the vast
majority of the world, the Bitcoin main
chain is too expensive, right? At least
times of congestion. So there is a need
to move some of this off of the Bitcoin
main chain over time. But I think when
you talk about it as a money, that's
what actually got me really excited
because decentralized money, the TAM is
enormous, right? And we all get really
excited about that. And I've got a lot
of very expensive coffees from like, you
know, around that that time frame. But I
think that was what was so exciting
about it is that it it was peer-to-peer.
was that there was no central bank of
Bitcoin like you could just go create
and that's when we saw a lot of like the
first use cases of trying to use Bitcoin
for spending and that really opened up I
think a lot of people's attention to
what Bitcoin could be but then we've
deviated pretty far from that over time
and that's okay store of value is a
enormous use case even if we never make
it to medium of exchange so once you got
to Coinbase without you know going into
details about your experience at
Coinbase if you don't want to but what
did you feel was lacking in centralized
exchanges at the
centralized exchange business is really
profitable and like a super interesting
business and like I you know really
enjoyed my time there. Met a lot of
amazing people but at least from my like
view at the time. What were you doing
there exactly? So I ran money movements
engineering. So it was like on all the
on and off platform fun movements which
was a lot of fun. We got to chase bad
guys. We got to get a lot of like money
onto the onto the platform. Company went
public during that time. Like I I really
enjoyed it. But I would say that
Coinbase has always had a little bit
more of like an Ethereum lens to it. And
you can see Bass now I think is like
more or less eating Ethereum and they've
done a ton of good for the crypto
ecosystem at large but also the Ethereum
in particular. My you know kind of bent
has always been more of the Bitcoin side
and I've always more identified as like
kind of more of a Bitcoin maxi and and
all that sort of thing as time has gone
on. I don't have that view today but
I've always identified more with kind of
that view of of crypto. And that's what
originally got me so excited about in
the first part. So it was going back to
first principles while taking a lot of
the best lessons that we learned from
Ethereum. Like the reason I decided to
do this in my career in 2017 was because
of Ethereum. It was okay, we have this
money in terms of Bitcoin that's totally
decentralized, but it wasn't really
programmable. Ethereum when we had the
first tokens, etc. was wow, you have
programmable money for the first time.
That's this amazing Lego block that you
can build off of. And that was really
kind of the genesis of putting all that
prehistory into one place and that
became core.
I talked to Adam back before and you
know he is the Bitcoin OG and he talked
about when the Satoshi white paper came
out. A lot of cyberpunk people actually
hated it because it was too transparent.
There's no privacy. You know how they
actually like privacy and it's on the
blockchain and everything you can see
everything publicly. What is your view
when you read the white paper at the
time? I don't think I was as focused on
privacy to be honest. But I think it now
has become a big focus area for me.
Private Bitcoin transactions are kind of
the holy grail and if not private maybe
you know confidential and I think that's
what we're seeing some interesting
experimentation on. You know that you
know David and Bonnie are transacting
maybe not what they're transacting or
how much and that's fairly compliant
with like most regulatory regimes. We
can't do that on Bitcoin. I think we
like have lost that time to add privacy
to Bitcoin. It's probably a good thing
potentially that we never did. That's
hotly debated, if you will. But I think
systems like core could potentially have
opt-in privacy for these transactions,
and that would be very useful, not just
for sending stables, but for also
sending Bitcoin. But I totally
appreciate what Adam is saying. And I
think private transactions are, you
know, a human right, if you will, but
we've never been able to fully do that
in a way that's compliant. And if you
look at Monero, Zcash, etc., like having
private transactions led to a lot of
issues um with regulators. So, it's some
sort of efficient frontier there that I
think we're still working through, but I
do think solutions like core that allow
you to put your Bitcoin to work could
have optin privacy or opt-in
confidentiality. And that's something
we're very excited about. I I never
really understood the use case of
privacy. Okay, let's say I'm making
transactions and I don't want my wife to
know and I want to use my credit card.
What else do I use? I don't know. I
don't know about your individual
like like marriage situation. Don't
bring your family problem here. Yeah, I
don't know about that one. So, I'm going
to like, you know, get go pretty far to
the side of that one. Um, but but I
think in general, like I don't know that
you'd want your credit card statement to
be on public display. Sure. And that's
effectively how blockchains work today,
right? And I think that's just a it's
very useful in some ways because it
allows you to have a decentralized
ledger that everybody can check and and
all that sort of stuff. But I think if
you have the ability to say that I don't
want things to be public unless I choose
to, that's a strictly better solution.
And I think it's also what we've gotten
used to in normal life, right? right?
Like when you swipe a credit card and
that sort of stuff, it doesn't get
broadcast for everyone else to see. So,
we've kind of inverted that model. And
the other like weird part about
blockchains is like you as the payer are
the ones that pay the fees versus like
the merchant et like it's inverted in a
lot of these different ways. And that
makes it difficult to make it skumorphic
with existing products and services that
we have. So, I think you'll start to see
over time more and more of that become
kind of more like the legacy system
which actually has some better
guarantees and better principles um yeah
that we have today. All right. Good. If
there is this privacy tech on top of it,
does that mean if a hacker hack your
fund now, you can't trace it? Depends on
how the privacy is implemented. So, and
that's like kind of a copout answer, but
I I'll try to explain it. Um so if you
go to like systems like Monero um which
you know historically are very um
resilient in terms of privacy you have
issues when you have hacks and that's
like it's very difficult and that's one
of the reasons that they've had issues
with regulators because you can't
actually tell who's how much money are
people sending and all that sort of
thing. kind of the new more like cutting
edge let's call it are these like
confidential systems and the
confidential systems tend to have
something like an auditor key and the
idea is to everyone externally who is
not an auditor all that we can see is
you two are transacting we don't know
what we don't know how much but if you
have this auditor key it all is now
public so not that it's public to the
chain but public to the auditor and
that's very useful for like AML KYC etc
compliance and I think that might be the
efficient frontier for a lot of these
things and that probably meets a lot of
folks's goals, not maybe the pure cipher
punk goal where you know that's more
Monero I would say. Um but I think it's
all about kind of the practical
realities of where we're at but there is
some really amazing technology that's
coming to light on that and I'm very
excited about it. It sounds less
decentralized. So that would not be a
focus.
It's still decentralized but somebody
holds the key. Somebody holds the key
not for the transaction but just how to
read it. Right. it it's still like the
transaction is it's just you have this
one actor that can introspect into the
system. So, okay. So, let me give you an
example. Okay. So, like let's imagine
that um trying to think of how to work
in David's, you know, family situation.
Uh yes, but let's say you have my
non-existent wife is watching. Be
careful. Okay, perfect. Perfect. Uh so,
let's say you're going to build like
decentralized Venmo or something, right?
Um, and you want to have this like
really high throughput, really awesome
interface that everyone's using,
whatever else, but you also want to be
you're also subject to like US
compliance restrictions or something.
Yes. Right. All those transactions are
be totally decentralized your protocol.
Yeah. But should the you know government
come in or whatever, you can then say,
"Oh, indeed this was not like an OFAC
restricted piece or whatever." So it's
no less decentralized in terms of the
transactions, there is the ability to
introspect and that might be the
efficient frontier of how you can
actually get to like practical privacy.
And I think what we've learned over time
is like there are some trade-offs that
have to be made in order to get some of
the different pieces that you want out
of these systems. And for some people
that's probably a better compromise than
being purely in public. But ultimately,
you know, you'll have to make the
products and decisions. In my view, it's
no worse than what you currently have.
Is this conversation completely moot
once CBDC's become effective? Oh man. Uh
CBDC's I'm not super long on to be
honest. M I think maybe we'll see some
in like some countries over the next few
years, but I think it creates a whole
lot of other issues. Uh and I think we
haven't like fully appreciated what full
CDBC's will will do because especially
in an area of like you know tons of fiat
debasement etc. CBDC's naturally go to
like censorship. Um you'll go to like
you know financial inclusion problems
and then you get to capital controls
like it spirals really quickly and I
don't know that that's a good thing and
I think we will have quite a bit of
resistance to things like CDBTC's around
the world. I think Trump, correct me if
he did ban CBDCs, did he not no CBC? He
he has banned it. The US it's always
like you know who's in power? How does
it flip-flop whatever but there's other
countries like I believe Brazil that are
like actively experimenting with CDBC's.
Sure. So, we will I mean we'll see this
all get you know kind of litigated and
you know figured out in the courts. Um
but it's it's going to be challenging
and I think if we do go down that road
decentralized blockchains become that
much more important right um for for
more than just like kind of general um
you know unstable currency situations. I
read this chart that over 90% of the
world is either experimenting or
building CBDC or interested. At least
90% is a high number.
Super high number. I think it's like a
it's the dream for for a government,
right? Like any sort of government would
love to have perfect auditability,
perfect verifiability, capital control,
censorship. Like it's 1984 like on on
steroids, right? So like I'm not
surprised that people are experimenting
and they're like trying to figure stuff
out. Whether or not that gets
implemented, I think is a very very
different story, but it makes sense of
why governments would want it. It's the
exact reason why citizens don't want it,
right? Like like that you have this very
natural tension between those different
things. And I think uh the US is is
leading in a lot of these areas as David
mentioned where said, "Hey, we won't
have any CBDC's. We're now moving
towards stablecoin uh legislation that
will allow you to have decentralized
money." And I think the more and more
that uh becomes popularized, the more
opposition you will have to some of
these other, you know, CBDC's, which I
think are pretty dangerous overall. I'm
just imagining if, you know, a person in
government, they're like, how do I
control? How do I manage my country,
then I will try to push for CBDC and
I'll probably try to convince the people
that this is good. without going into
too much of like philosophy whatever
government and central planning hasn't
worked out too well uh in in in most
cases um so I think giving like full
autonomy over like individual
transactions and that sort of stuff
becomes really really bad from a uh from
a government perspective because because
now like again like in most systems we
want them to be egotary and everything
else but in reality and look at the last
administration in the US not everybody
is treated the same and Okay, if I don't
like some political party or they just
won or whatever, okay, what what do I do
to disenfranchise them? Well, if I can
now block all of their transactions, you
now have a very different system. And
that amount of government control, I
think, is not beneficial in any system,
whether it's the US or otherwise,
because I think it naturally just gives
too much power down to the individual
level, and it becomes, you know, Black
Mirror, I think, you know, pretty
quickly. Yeah. Well, speaking of Black
Mirror in the future, is the future of
money dystopian or utopian? Just paint
us a picture for not just our
generation, but maybe our kids kids
generation. What does money look like?
Getting philosophical. I like this. Um,
so I think, and this is going to be like
kind of trit, but I think it really
depends on what you think the level of
like human productivity and human
progress is over like the next, let's
call it 5 to 10 years. And I think if we
continue to see this productivity boom
that we're seeing primarily driven by AI
right now, I think money will change
significantly because I think we can get
to a spot not far from now where agents
and otherwise are actually going out
there and working on our behalf and a
lot of these are microtransactions that
we are never really kind of privy to,
right? It's kind of going on in this,
you know, asynchronous world. And I
think that's just a totally new concept
that we're not ready for. And I think
that's also where blockchains really
shine because you have the ability to
trustlessly exchange value amongst all
these different participants. But I
think on a general like like let's put
let's put that as like the the Rosie
case, right? Where it's like
productivity increases such a level most
people don't have to work and you know
all of that is kind of going well. I
think on the other side you're going to
have more more fiat debasement and
you're going to have these issues where
the value prop of Bitcoin becomes that
much more interesting. And I think in in
that world things like Bitcoin become
that much more sacred because it becomes
a lot more dystopian where your you know
asset of whatever country you're in is
just constantly getting devalued. Asset
prices go up but everything else you
know from a affordability point of view
gets inflated away. And that's a really
dangerous setup. Without going too much
into like economics I think we might be
on like a little bit of an unstoppable
you know debt roller coaster. One of the
coolest concepts of money ever I've seen
is used in science fiction in Star Trek.
They don't actually have money. They use
credits for intergalactic trade, but
because they have these like
replicators, you can print food or
whatever you want, whenever you want.
So, you don't need a form of trade. You
don't need a medium of exchange when you
can just create your own stuff, right? I
mean, just that comment just I'm just
trying to get a facial reaction out of
Yeah.
You're going to get my my face going all
different directions. That's my last
question. I promise. I love it. I love
it. Uh yeah, I don't I don't really
remember Star Trek. I've seen like
various, you know, like William Shatner
episodes like But you've seen like you
can like I want steak and then the steak
comes out. So but this is what I would
say is like a dramatic extension of like
that AI productivity boom, right? Right.
Which is like you don't have to work.
Everything is there's no scarcity. Like
you get to that world, yeah, you don't
really need money because everything's
like purely abundant. That's it. But but
I think it's and this is where you get
to that kind of that contrasting view of
like okay do we live in that world or do
we live in unstoppable debt roller
coaster where the only thing in the
world that has any value anymore is
Bitcoin and essentially all trusted
intermediaries are in really bad places
like those are two totally opposite you
know um like kind of states of the world
but there's some sort of like weighted
probability of like where are we heading
on what time lane and and that's
something that we all should be
balancing like those two different
modalities in terms of thinking what we
get to we all prefer the Star Trek you
know kind of view of the universe But
it's really hard to weight that against
like all these other macro shifts. Sure.
Based on what you just said, plus what
Brian Johnson said, we don't die and AI
now works for us. I love this interview.
Um, we don't have to work now. We have
so much time. What do we do? Like what
is that generation like? It's a great
question. Um, and I I really wonder what
that looks like. Like having seen people
go into like retirement mode where like
they don't have as much to do anymore.
becomes this like I don't know
threequarter life crisis where you like
kind of have to figure out you know what
you want to do and that sort of thing
and I think that is something that
people will naturally tend to and I
think it will be a challenge like I
don't know like you sit on the beach and
like drink tea drinks whatever like for
all all the time I don't know um but I
think that's like an existential
question I'm hopeful that there's still
these society level improvements that
people can keep making whether it's for
you know monetary reasons or otherwise
in your world of perfect abundance like
you probably don't have that same goal
but it might be just pushing like
humanity forward in other ways, which
would be pretty cool. But I I don't know
if there's an answer to that. And if
Brian's right, we're all going to live
to be like 150. So, we're going to have
to like figure out how that all plays
out. Stake more Bitcoin till you're 150.
Should be like some sort of like stake
and stake, you know, where like, you
know, you're eating a steak and you're
like staking your Bitcoin, you know,
stake Bitcoin. Come out, put it back
into Dell. Thank you so much. It was a
lot of fun, Rich. Nice to meet you.
Thanks so much. Yeah. Appreciate it.